<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- vim: set sw=4 et tw=100 ai spell :-->

<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
"http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">

<html lang="en" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <head>
        <title>LEARN YOURSELF A GTD</title>
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="lyagtd.css" type="text/css" />
        <link href='http://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Droid+Serif:regular,italic,bold,bolditalic' rel='stylesheet' type='text/css' />
        <link href='http://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Droid+Sans:regular,bold' rel='stylesheet' type='text/css' />
        <style type="text/css">
            body {
            font-family: 'Droid Serif', serif;
            }
        </style>
        <script src="hyphenate.js" type="text/javascript" />
    </head>
    <body>
        <div class="topheader">
            LEARN YOURSELF A GTD<br />
            OR:<br />
            “GTD IN 15 MINUTES”
        </div>

        <div class="header">
            <div class="headerimg">
                <img src="images/slinky.png" alt="welcome!" />
            </div>

            <div class="toc">
                <h2>Table of contents</h2>
                <ol>
                    <li><a href="#whatisgtd">What is “GTD”?</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#theinlist">The “<span class="listname">in</span>“ list</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#processingtheinlist">Processing the “<span class="listname">in</span>” list</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#thenextactionslist">The “<span class="listname">next actions</span>” list</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#thewaitingforlist">The “<span class="listname">waiting for</span>” list</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#projects">Projects</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#contexts">Contexts</a>
                        <ul>
                            <li><a href="#agendacontexts">Agenda contexts</a></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li><a href="#thesomedaymaybelist">The “<span class="listname">some day/maybe</span>” list</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#calendar">Calendar</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#weeklyreview">Weekly review</a>
                        <ul>
                            <li><a href="#triggerlists">Trigger Lists</a></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li><a href="#gettingittowork">Getting it to work</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#tools">Tools</a>
                        <ul>
                            <li><a href="#readreviewfolder">Read/review folder</a></li>
                            <li><a href="#ticklerfile">Tickler file</a></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li><a href="#aboutthisguide">About this guide</a></li>
                </ol>
            </div>
        </div>

        <div class="hyphenate"> <!-- hyphenate from here -->

            <a name="whatisgtd" />
            <h1>What is “GTD”?</h1>

            <p>
                GTD – or “Getting things done” – is a framework for organising
                and tracking your tasks and projects.  Its aim is a bit higher than just
                “getting things done”, though.  (It should have been called “Getting things
                done in a much better way than just letting things happen, which often turns out
                not to be very cool at all”.)  Its aim is to make you have 100% trust in a
                system for collecting tasks, ideas, and projects – both vague things like
                <span class="action">“invent greatest thing ever”</span> and concrete things
                like <span class="action">“call Ada 25 August to discuss cheesecake
                    recipe”</span>.  <i>Everything</i>!
            </p>

            <p>
                Sound like all other run-of-the-mill to-do list systems, you say? Well in
                many ways it is, but there is more to it, and it's really simple.  Promise! So
                please read on.
            </p>

            <p>
                One of the basic assumptions of GTD is that you are dumb – or rather,
                that your subconsciousness is quite dumb when it comes to thinking about things
                you <i>should</i> have done.  Like knowing you need to buy more flour and sugar,
                but forgetting to remind you when you actually are in the store.
            </p>

            <p>
                A great part of the “magic” is to convert both tasks and whims into
                <i>physical</i> and <i>visible</i> <strong>actions</strong>.
            </p>

            <p>
                What GTD gives you – when understood and implemented properly –
                is a foolproof system for keeping track of what you need to do, should do, or
                should <i>consider</i> to do. When your system and your trust in your system is
                in place your your subconsciousness will stop keeping track of all the things
                you need to do and constantly reminding you.  This reduces stress, frees up precious brain time to more productive thinking –
                maybe even save <i>real</i> time so that you have more time for ballet
                lessons, painting class, roller-blading, or whatever you kids do these days.
            </p>

            <img src="images/lists.png" alt="lists!" style="width: 240px;" />
            <p>
                Awesome! So how does it actually work? It works by using special yoga
                techniques and daily mental exercises.  No, haha! Just kidding.  It works by
                simply maintaining lists, which every kid with paper and a pencil can do.
                Even computers can maintain lists these days!

            </p>

            <p>
                You will have to make the following lists:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li> <span class="listname">In</span></li>
                <li> <span class="listname">Next actions</span> (probably several)</li>
                <li> <span class="listname">Waiting for</span></li>
                <li> <span class="listname">Projects</span></li>
                <li> <span class="listname">Some day/maybe</span></li>
            </ul>

            <p>
                These lists will be reviewed regularly and form the backbone of the GTD system.
                Their workings are described below.  In addition to the lists you will need a
                <span class="calendar">calendar</span> which lets you write down both date and time
                bound tasks/events.
            </p>

            <div class="important">
                <p>
                    This run-through of the GTD method is meant to be brief. It's written from one
                    person's perspective and other people would probably assess the importance of
                    different aspects of GTD differently.
                </p>

                <p>
                    If you want a complete overview of GTD you would be wise to read David
                    Allen's book which formalised the method he developed: <strong>“Getting Things
                    Done: The Art of Stress-Free Productivity”</strong> (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0142000280?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=erlehamb-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0142000280">Amazon</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=erlehamb-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0142000280" width="1" height="1" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />,
                    <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000WH7PKY?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=erlehamb-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B000WH7PKY">Kindle Store</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=erlehamb-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B000WH7PKY" width="1" height="1" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />,
                    <a href="http://www.bookdepository.co.uk/book/9780142000281/Getting-Things-Done?a_aid=ehamberg">Bookdepository</a>,
                    <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=LAx_PwAACAAJ&amp;dq=getting+things+done">Google Books</a>,
                    <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Getting_Things_Done">Wikipedia</a>).
                </p>
            </div>

            <a name="theinlist" />
            <h1>The “<span class="listname">in</span>“ list</h1>

            <p>
                The <span class="listname">in</span> list is where you capture ideas and tasks as
                they occur to you.  Either by your boss telling you to bake her a carrot cake, or by
                you seeing a poster for a circus you want to see.  The barrier for adding something
                to your <span class="listname">in</span> list should be as low as possible – jot it
                down in a notebook or press the right buttons on your pocket telephone.  While I
                have called it <i>the</i> <span class="listname">in</span> list, It is no problem to
                have more than one.  Maybe a computer program for when you are in front of a
                computer and a notebook for when you loiter outside the mall?  The important thing
                is that you are able to write down things as they occur to you.  We want to offload
                work from the brain, remember?
            </p>

            <p>
                When you first start to use GTD you should take an hour to write down all things you
                want to – or have to – do.  These <i>open loops</i> as Allen calls them include
                <i>all</i> things that aren't as they should be or where they should be.  Do you
                need to replace your toothbrush? Return the tea cup you borrowed from your aunt
                Trillian? Should you repaint your bed in another colour?  All these things should go
                on your <span class="listname">in</span> list.
            </p>

            <a name="processingtheinlist" />
            <h1>Processing the “<span class="listname">in</span>” list</h1>

            <div class="remember">
                If you have just started to use GTD and collected tonnes of items in your <span
                class="listname">in</span> list during the initial “brain-emptying”, this
                process can take a while.  However, after this the <span class="listname">in</span>
                list will be processed continuously.
            </div>

            <p>
                The items on your <span class="listname">in</span> list should be processed one by
                one in the order they appear on your list.  When processing at an item in your <span
                class="listname">in</span> list the first question you need to ask is <strong>is it
                actionable?</strong> – in other words, do you need to <i>do</i> something?  If the
                answer is NO, you either throw it away if you no longer need it, keep it as
                reference material (“I will probably need this article again some day...“), add it
                to a ”some day/maybe list” (for things like <span class="action">“learn
                Indonesian”</span>), or <strong>incubate</strong> it.  Wait, what! Sit on it?  Yes,
                sort of.  If it's something that you want to remind yourself of later (“I really
                didn't understand this article, I should have a look at it again in two weeks”) it
                should go into your calendar or your tickler file.  Don't know what a tickler file
                is?  Worry not, it is introduced below and its weird name explained.
            </p>

            <p>
                Now, if the item you're currently processing <i>is</i> actionable – in other
                words: something should be done about it – you should ask the question “<i>what
                is the next action?</i>”  <strong>The next action needs to be a <i>physical</i> and
                <i>visible</i> action</strong>.  In other words, not <span class="action">“plan cake
                lottery”</span>, but <span class="action">“e-mail Arthur and Camille and remind them
                to bake their cakes”</span>.
            </p>

            <div class="important">
                This very thing – that next actions should be the next <strong>physical,
                visible</strong> action to move the project closer to its goal – is perhaps
                <i>the</i> most important “rule” in GTD.  By using a few extra seconds to come up
                with what <i>physically</i> needs to be done, you make sure that your “next action”
                lists will only contain the things you can choose to do at any moment.  The
                “pre-processing” has already been done (the actions themselves may very well be
                planning tasks, though) and this greatly lowers the resistance to <i>do</i> the
                things.
            </div>

            <p>
                When you have determined the next action you should consider if it takes two
                minutes or less to do it.  If it does, do it right away.  (Things like and <span
                class="action">“e-mail funny cat video to grandma”</span>.)  The reason for this is
                simple: if the action takes two minutes or less, the overhead of tracking it will be
                very large compared to how long it takes to just <i>do</i> it.  If it takes more
                than two minutes you should <strong>delegate</strong> it if appropriate – noting
                what was delegated and when on a <span class="listname">waiting for</span> list, or
                add it to your own <span class="listname">next actions</span> list.  Unless your
                secret superpower is delegation, this is probably where most things will end up.
            </p>

            <p>
                To summarise, when processing your <span class="listname">in</span> list(s), you
                should follow this procedure:
            </p>

            <div class="important">
                <ul>
                    <li>If the item is NOT “actionable”:
                        <p>
                            Throw it away, archive it for future reference, or put it on your “some
                            day/maybe” list.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>If item IS “actionable”:
                        <ul>
                            <li>Work out the next physical, visible action.</li>
                            <li>If this action will it take 2 minutes or less:
                                <p>
                                    Do it!
                                </p>

                            </li>
                            <li>If this action will it take more than 2 minutes:
                                <ul>
                                    <li>Delegate it and add it to your <span class="listname">waiting for</span> list.
                                        <p>
                                            OR

                                        </p>
                                    </li>
                                    <li>Add it to your <span class="listname">next actions</span> list of things to be done.</li>
                                </ul>
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </div>

            <a name="thenextactionslist" />
            <h1>The “<span class="listname">next actions</span>” list</h1>

            <p>
                So what's the <span class="listname">next actions</span> list?  Well, uh, a list of
                your next actions, obviously.  Another name for these actions is
                “as-soon-as-possible actions” – it is simply those things from which you will pick
                out what to work on when you are not watching funny cat videos on Youtube or playing
                Farmville.
            </p>

            <a name="thewaitingforlist" />
            <h1>The “<span class="listname">waiting for</span>” list</h1>

            <p>
                When you delegate work to others, send an e-mail you expect or need to be replied
                to, order something, or have a task that is “blocked” because you are waiting for
                someone else to do something, it should be written down on your <span
                    class="listname">waiting for</span> list.  These items should always be stamped
                with the current date so that you'll be able to e-mail your co-worker
                Marvin and say “I'm still waiting for the WTF report you said you'd finish within a
                month.  That was 32 days ago!”.
            </p>

            <a name="projects" />
            <h1>Projects</h1>

            <p>
                If your still with me you might have worried that a <span class="action">“research
                artificial intelligence textbooks”</span> action on your <span class="listname">next
                actions</span> list is all that is written down about your plan to take over the
                world.  Wouldn't it be easy to lose track once that action is done and erased from
                your list? Yes, it kinda would...  That's where the <span
                    class="listname">projects</span> list comes in.
            </p>

            <p>
                GTD's definition of a project is very broad.  It defines any objective that requires
                more than one action as a project.  These projects should go on your <span
                    class="listname">projects</span> list.  This list is simply a list of project
                titles and – if you like – descriptions and intended outcomes of the projects.
            </p>

            <a name="contexts" />
            <h1>Contexts</h1>

            <img src="images/computer.png" alt="computer!" style="width: 220px;" />

            <p>
                Contexts are “tags” you put on the items on your <span class="listname">next
                actions</span> lists saying where the action can be done, or what equipment you need
                to perform it.  An action can be “tagged” with a context in several ways; the
                easiest is probably to simply have different <span class="listname">next
                actions</span> lists – one for each context. If you use a new-fangled electronic
                list manager you can often have “smart” lists for each tags – giving the same
                result. (With so-called smartphones it's probably even possible to use its location
                awareness to only present actions whose context match your current location. If so:
                that is amazing! We live in the future!)
            </p>

            <p>
                It is common to prefix contexts with an ‛@’ which makes sense when the context is a
                location, but should just be thought of as a notation in other cases. Examples of
                contexts are <span class="context">@ home</span>, <span
                    class="context">@ computer</span>, and <span class="context">@ office</span>.
            </p>

            <h3>Examples of actions and their contexts</h3>

            <div class="example">
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Action</th>
                        <th>Context</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><span class="action">Buy more rainbow-coloured dog food</span></td>
                        <td><span class="context">@ city</span> or <span class="context">@ store</span></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><span class="action">Browse cuteoverload.com</span></td>
                        <td><span class="context">@ computer</span> or <span class="context">@
                                the world wide webs</span></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><span class="action">Smile to a stranger</span></td>
                        <td><span class="context">@ everywhere</span></td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </div>

            <p>
                How many contexts you need depend on how many next actions you will have and how
                your work day looks like.  The important thing is to be able to assess – at a glance
                – what your possible actions are depending on where you physically are and what
                equipment you have available.  It can also be a good idea to make an “everywhere”
                context for things you can do no matter where you are (“FOO”).
            </p>

            <a name="agendacontexts" />
            <h2>Agenda contexts</h2>

            <p>
                If you have regular meetings with people, it can be beneficial to have “agenda
                contexts” – one for each person – where you write down the things you want to talk
                about during the next meeting as they occur. For example, if you have a weekly
                meeting with Foobert, you might consider having a “<span
                    class="context">@ Foobert Agenda</span>” context.  These contexts will of course
                change along with changing teams/managers/supervisor, etc.
            </p>

            <a name="thesomedaymaybelist" />
            <h1>The “<span class="listname">some day/maybe</span>” list</h1>

            <p>
                You don't want to lose your million-dollar idea of making a “jumping to conclusions”
                mat that lets people jump to conclusions, but since this is a project you want to
                realise when you have more time you don't want to have it “pollute” your <span
                    class="listname">next actions</span> lists or your list of <span
                    class="listname">projects</span> either. (Remember that the <span
                    class="listname">next actions</span> only contains the things that should be
                done as soon as possible and that your <span class="listname">projects</span> list
                will be reviewed regularly to make sure that all projects have at least one next
                action.)
            </p>

            <p>
                This is where the <span class="listname">some day/maybe</span> list comes it.  This
                list simply contains ideas and projects you <i>might</i> want to realise at some
                time in the future. This is where both <span class="action">“replace ugly painting
                    in bed room”</span> and <span class="action">“start a cult”</span> should go.
                (Assuming – of course – that you don't want to do either of those things right now.)
            </p>

            <a name="calendar" />
            <h1>Calendar</h1>

            <img src="images/calendar.png" alt="calendar" style="width: 220px;" />

            <p>
                The <span class="calendar">calendar</span> is for things you <i>have</i> to do on a
                certain date or at a certain time, and <i>nothing else</i>!  That's right; no
                putting <span class="action">“install Bonzibudddy“</span> on your calendar for next
                Wednesday if you just <i>now</i> think you <i>want</i> to have it done then.
            </p>

            <p>
                Why?  By only having items which really are time and date sensitive on your <span
                    class="calendar">calendar</span> it will be more useful since it will actually
                tell you the things you <i>have</i> to do a certain day without being “diluted“ with
                other items.  The thing you <i>want</i> to do will be on your <span
                    class="listname">next actions</span> list any way, so you will be reminded about
                it and have the chance to do it anyway if you have the time.
            </p>

            <a name="weeklyreview" />
            <h1>Weekly review</h1>

            <p>
                Allen calls the weekly review a “critical factor for success” and he is not joking.
                If you start using the GTD framework and you are not a robot, things will start to
                slip. You will complete the next action of a project and forget to add a new, next
                action for that project. You will forget to remove next actions that you – if you
                really thought about it – know that you won't do in the near future because more
                important things have shown up.
            </p>

            <p>
                <i>The weekly review</i> should be done – you guessed it – once per week. It will
                take a while, so you should ideally set off some time in advance, for example Friday
                or Sunday afternoon. When doing the weekly review you should at least do the
                following:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>Make sure each project has at least one next action.</li>
                <li>Make sure that each action on your <span class="listname">next
                        actions</span> list is <i>actually</i> something you want to do if
                    you have the time. If not, move it (and/or the project it belongs
                    to) to your <span class="listname">someday/maybe</span> list.</li>
                <li>Look through your someday/maybe list and see if some
                    projects/actions should be moved to the list of current projects/the
                    <span class="listname">next actions</span> list. If creating a new
                    project on your <span class="listname">projects</span> list, make
                    sure to find its next physical, visible action and put it on the
                    <span class="listname">next actions</span> list.</li>
            </ul>

            <a name="triggerlists" />
            <h2>Trigger lists</h2>
            <p>
                When doing the weekly review it can be a good idea to work through a “trigger list”.
                A trigger list is simply a list of key words to “trigger” you to remember any open
                loops you still haven't captured in your system. A trigger list could look like the
                following:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>Boss</li>
                <li>Co-workers</li>
                <li>Projects started, not completed</li>
                <li>Projects that need to be started</li>
                <li>People I need to get back to</li>
                <li>…</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                When working through your trigger list, put anything that you remember in your <span
                    class="listname">in</span> list to be processed afterwards.

            </p>

            <p>
                An example of a trigger list can be seen at <a
                    href="http://lifehacker.com/5611657/use-a-weekly-review-list-to-stay-a-step-ahead-this-semester">
                <i>Lifehacker</i>'s trigger list for students</a>. You probably want to
                customise your own list as you get more experience and learn what works best for
                <i>you</i>.
            </p>

            <a name="gettingittowork" />
            <h1>Getting it to work</h1>

            <p>
                To actually get your GTD system to work there are some important “rules” to follow.
                ...
            </p>

            <p>
                It is important that you have <strong>hard edges</strong> between your lists, and
                between your <span class="listname">next actions</span> lists.
            </p>

            <a name="tools" />
            <h1>Tools</h1>

            <p>
                The read/review folder and tickler file are two tools which – while they aren't
                directly part of the GTD method – may be beneficial to use together with GTD.
            </p>

            <a name="readreviewfolder" />
            <h2>Read/review folder</h2>

            <p>
                You will probably have quite a few <span class="action">“read [some
                document]”</span> actions on their <span class="listname">next actions</span> list.
                A read/review folder is simply a physical folder you carry around, containing the
                papers, documents, and anything else you want to read.  The idea is to have this
                material available whenever you have a few minutes to kill. In the dentist's waiting
                room?  Waiting for your food at a café?  Both perfect opportunities to peruse the
                paper on <i>Periophthalmus modestus</i> phylogeny or pretend to read the memo from
                your boss!
            </p>

            <p>
                It is really imporant to have “sharp edges” here, too. Only the things you actually
                want to read when you have the time should be put in this folder so that you
                actually <i>will</i> pick it up during those little windows of free time that show
                up during the day.
            </p>

            <a name="ticklerfile" />
            <h2>Tickler file</h2>

            <img src="images/tickle.png" alt="tickle!" style="width: 280px;" />
            <p>
                This strangely-named concept is simply a collection of 43 file folders. Why 43?
                Because that means that you can have one for each of the <strong>31</strong> days of
                a month plus one for each of the <strong>12</strong> months of the year.  If you're
                reaching for your calculator now – just trust me on the number 43.
            </p>

            <p>
                So what are these folders used for? The idea is that you can place physical items
                you will need on a specific day (tickets for the concert), reminders of things you
                should do on a specific date (remember, the calendar is only for things that
                <i>have</i> to be done on a specific date/time), or the notes from the lecture you
                didn't really understand (“I will want to review these in a week when my
                subconsciousness has chewed on it for a while”).
            </p>

            <p>
                Every day when you get up, you open the folder with the current date. You then
                pocket your concert tickets, decides that you <i>do</i> want to take the dog to the
                dog hairdresser today, but push the lecture notes back three days since you don't
                have time right now. Having emptied the folder, you place it in the back, bringing
                tomorrow's folder to the front. At the end of each month, you open the folder for
                the new month and deal with its contents – like putting items in the correct day
                folders.
            </p>

            <p>
                The tickler file thus provides a way to send yourself reminders in the future –
                “tickling” your memory. Aaaaah!
            </p>

            <a name="aboutthisguide" />
            <h1>About this guide</h1>

            <p>
                This guide was written to serve as a simple, hands-on guide to the “getting things
                done” method.
            </p>

            <p>
                The guide's visual style was inspired by Miran Lipovača's excellent guide to the
                Haskell programming language “<a href="http://learnyouahaskell.com">Learn You a
                Haskell for Great Good!</a>”.

            </p>

        </div> <!-- end of hyphenation -->

        <!--
            TODO
            * more illustrations
            * change title
        -->

</body>
</html>
